Guide to the William McFee Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Acquisitions, 1948-1972 and 1983, 1862-1966, undated; 36.91; (98 boxes) + 1 art
  - Personal Papers, 1862-1966, undated
    - McFee family, 1862-1932 (Box 83)
    - Other personal papers, 1895-1965; 2 (Box 83)
    - Other personal papers, 1895-1965 (Box 86 (Oversize))
    - Scrapbook, circa 1920s-1930s (Box 84 (Oversize))
      Contains clippings about McFee; photographs of McFee, family, and friends; fragments of writings by McFee; and ephemera relating to marine engineering and travel
    - Scrapbook, 1919-1936 (Box 85 (Oversize))
      Contains mostly clippings about McFee and clippings of his writings, with some correspondence and ephemera
  - Photographs and Other Visual Materials, 1931, undated
    Most photographs and drawings are portraits of McFee; also present are images of his family, friends, places of residence, and ships. Portraits of McFee include drawings by Arthur J. Elder and a bronze bust by Jason Sturm (Yale 1922).
    Additional photographs are present in the Correspondence subseries and in scrapbooks in the Personal Papers subseries.
    - Photographs of William McFee, undated; 5 (Box 87)
      Includes fragment of Harbours of Memory, autograph manuscript
    - Photographs of William McFee (Box 89 (Oversize))
    - Drawings of William McFee, undated; 3 (Box 87)
      Includes drawings by Arthur J. Elder; and woodblocks by unidentified artists
    - Drawings of William McFee, undated (Box 89 (Oversize))
    - Bronze bust of William McFee (Box 87a (Art))
      By Justin Sturm (Yale 1922)
    - Other photographs, undated; 4 (Box 87)
    - Other photographs, undated (Box 89 (Oversize))
    - Other drawings, undated (Box 87)
    - Other drawings, 1931, undated (Box 89 (Oversize))
    - Photograph albums, 2 (Box 88)
  - James T. Babb Research Materials, 1924-1966, undated
    Contains materials relating to Babb's A Bibliography of the Writings of William McFee. Correspondence includes letters to and from McFee, and with vendors, concerning Babb's collection of McFee books and manuscripts.
    Additional correspondence relating to Babb's research is in Third-Party Correspondence in the Correspondence subseries.
    - Checklist and notes, 1939, undated (Box 90)
    - Correspondence, 1924-1966; 9 (Box 90)
    - Card file, undated (Box 91)
  - Restricted Fragile Material, 1962-1963
    Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - McFee's Birthday Talk (1 of 2 reels), 1962 June 16 -1963 June 15; 1; 00:56:08; There is static on the tape. (Box 92, Item barcode 39002091394628)
      This audiotape reel relates to McFee's 75th birthday in 1956.
    - McFee's Birthday Talk, Part 2 (2 of 2 reels), 1963 June 15; 1; 00:44:06; The program is distorted at times. (Box 92, Item barcode 39002091394636)
    - Writings/"Off Nantucket" (Box 106 (Oversize))
    - Writings/Other Writings/Unidentified (novel) (Box 107 (Oversize))
  - Restricted
    Restricted until 2033 September 24. For more information, consult the appropriate curator.
    - Correspondence and writings, 8 (Box 93)
    - Correspondence and writings, 3 (Box 94)
    - Correspondence and writings, 5 (Box 95)
- Acquisitions, 1979-2002, 1897-1965, undated; 3; (9 boxes)
  Organized into five groupings: May 1995 Acquisition; January 1996 Acquisition; October 2000 Acquisition; February 2002 Acquisition; and Other Acquisitions.
  Consists of individual accessions acquired 1979-2002. Writings by McFee are autograph manuscript, unless otherwise noted.
  - May 1995 Acquisition, 1965, undated
    Purchased from William Reese on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 1995
    - Neufeld, Phillip (letters from McFee), undated (Box 96)
    - Sternberg, Samuel (letters from McFee), 1965 February 3 (Box 96)
    - "On the Malecon", undated (Box 96)
  - January 1996 Acquisition, 1897-1962, undated
    Purchased from David J. Holmes on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 1996.
    - Correspondence, 1927-1962
      - Barrell, Charles Wisner, 1943-1963; 3 (Box 97)
      - Hansen, Harry, 1922-1950 (Box 97)
      - MacDonald, Pirie, 1922-1942 (Box 97)
      - Targ, William, 1944, 1946 (Box 97)
      - Tutchings, Patricia MacDonald, 1942 (Box 97)
      - West, Herbert Faulkner, 1938-1959 (Box 97)
      - Whitman, Edmund, 1930-[1962] (Box 97)
      - Unsorted, 1927-1962 (Box 97)
    - Writings, 1897, undated
      - "Children of the Everlasting Sea." Typescript, undated (Box 97)
      - "A Curious Story", 1897 December 26 (Box 97)
      - The Gates of the Carribbean. Printed, undated (Box 97)
      - "The Scourge of the China Coast." Typescript, undated (Box 97)
      - "The Ship of Missing Men." Typescript, undated (Box 97)
      - "What to Do on Board a Lightship." Typescript, revised, undated (Box 97)
  - October 2000 Acquisition, 1928-1958, undated
    - Letter to an unidentified correspondent, 1928 April 13 (Box 98)
    - "David Copperfield" (radio broadcast), 1958 (Box 98)
    - Hassan by James Elroy Flecker (book review), undated (Box 98)
    - Tales of Hearsay by Joseph Conrad (book review), undated (Box 98)
    - Babb, James T., A Bibliography of the Writings of William McFee. Contract, 1931 (Box 98)
  - February 2002 Acquisition, 1931, undated
    Gift of Al Hirsch, 2002.
    - James T. Babb Research Materials, 1931, undated
      Contains materials relating to Babb's A Bibliography of the Writings of William McFee
      - A Bibliography of the Writings of William McFee. Typescript, undated (Box 99)
      - A Bibliography of the Writings of William McFee. Printed, 1931 (Box 99)
      - "A Catalogue of Books from the Library of William Beckford." Typescript, undated (Box 99)
      - Notes removed from card files, undated (Box 99)
      - McFee, William, "The Public Library of the High Seas." Printed, 1931 October (Box 99)
      - "Images From the Past: Family Memories From Our Old Family Films", undated; GENMSS991_0001; 1; 00:15:13 (Box 100, Item barcode 39002102317105)
        Use of original is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
        Films of McFee and his family
      - "Images From the Past: Family Memories From Our Old Family Films", undated; GENMSS991_0002; 1; This is a duplicate tape. It has not been digitized. (Box 100, Item barcode 39002102317113)
      - "Original, keep it", undated; GENMSS991_0003; 1; This is a duplicate tape. It has not been digitized. (Box 100, Item barcode 39002102317121)
        Use of originals is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
      - Master tape, Al Hirsch, 2001 February 6 and 2001 March 27; GENMSS991_0004; 1; This is a duplicate tape. It has not been digitized. (Box 100, Item barcode 39002102317139)
      - "William McFee; Ernest Hemingway; American authors" (card file), undated (Box 101)
      - "William McFee" (card file), undated (Box 102)
    - Restricted Fragile, undated
      - 16mm films, undated; 3 (Box 103)
  - Other Acquisitions, 1904-1940, undated
    - Correspondence, 1927-1940, undated
      - Feldkamp, Fred J. (to Homer Woodbridge), 1927-1938 (Box 104)
        Purchased from David J. Holmes on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 1996
      - VanderPoel, Halsted B. (from McFee), 1940 January 10 (Box 104)
        Gift of Halstead B. VanderPoel, 1979
      - Woodbridge, Homer E. (from McFee), 1927 August 23 (Box 104)
    - Writings, 1904-1938, undated
      - The Alien (novel), 1914; 2 (Box 104)
        Purchased from C. A. Stonehill on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 1981
        Published as Aliens
      - Casuals of the Sea (novel). Typescript, undated; 2 (Box 104)
        Accompanied by a note to Arthur J. Elder, 1923 April 26
      - "The Flaw" (short story), undated (Box 104)
        Purchased from Ballinger's Book Service on the Albert H. Childs Fund, 1979
      - The Gates of the Caribbean (adaptation for a radio broadcast), 1922 December 24 (Box 104)
        Read by McFee on WJZ (Newark, New Jersey), 1922 December 24
        Accompanied by a printed advertisement for the broadcast; and a letter from A. D. Moreford to McFee, 1922 December 18
      - Letters from an Ocean Tramp, 1904-1908 (Box 104)
      - Notes on Frederick Wicks, undated (Box 104)
        Purchased from Pharos Books on the Hubert Amer McGuire Memorial Fund, 2002
      - Oscar Wilde by Boris Brasol (book review), 1938 July (Box 104)
        Gift of Halsted B. VanderPoel, 1979